Guide to Macedonia troubles correspondence, 1882-1913 MS 128
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Macedonia Troubles correspondence
1882-1913
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Symonds, Arthur G.
MS 128
0.1 Linear Feet (1 folder)
This is a collection of 31 letters dated variously between 1882-1913, regarding the troubles in Macedonia, written to A. G. Symonds and others of the National Reform Union.
Biographical Note
Arthur G. Symonds was the Secretary of the National Reform Union in London, England during the time these letters were received. After the revival of Greek, Serbian, and Bulgarian statehood in the 19th century, the Ottoman lands in Europe that became identified as Macedonia, were contested by all three governments, leading to the creation in the 1890s and 1900s of rival armed groups who divided their efforts between fighting the Turks and one another. In 1912, the allied Balkan states of Bulgaria, Greece, Serbia and Montenegro declared war against Turkey.
A portion of this brief sketch was excerpted from wikipedia, accessed on July 9, 2008, http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Macedonia_%28region%29.
Scope and Contents
This is a collection of 31 letters in one folder, dated variously between 1882-1913, regarding the troubles in Macedonia, written to A. G. Symonds and others of the National Reform Union; letters are from Noel Buxton, G.O. Trevelyan, J. Biggar, Gladstone, Goldwin Smith, Lord Hugh Cecil, the Bishop of London ("deplorable state of things in Macedonia"); Montagu Butler, Earl Grey ("I fear that separate action of the British Government alone would be useless or worse"), R.B. Haldane ("public opinion is apathetic"), Drummond Wolff ("We are bound by our action in 1878 to secure the well-being and the freedom of the Christian and Non-Muslim populations of Turkey"), Hensley Henson, James Bryce, M. Javid, Turkish Statesman; The Archbishop of Canterbury; Randall Davidson (to the Bishop of Worcester condemning the outrages in the Balkans).
Access Restrictions
This material is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored onsite at the Woodson Research Center.
Acquisition Information
Purchased in July 1961 on the recommendation of Rice History Professor Hardin Craig.
Index Terms
Subjects
Political parties; Politics and government
Document Types
corrrespondence
Places
Europe -- Macedonia; Balkan Peninsula -- History
Subjects (Persons)
Cecil, Hugh Richard Heath, Lord; Bryce, James Bryce, Viscount; Banerjea, Surendranath, Sir; Haldane, R. B Haldane (Richard Burdon Haldane), Viscount; Grey of Fallodon, Edward Grey, Viscount; Gladstone, W. E. (William Ewart); Davidson, Randall Thomas; Trevelyan, George Otto, Sir; Noel-Buxton, Noel Noel-Buxton, Baron
- Series I: Letters, 1882-1889, 11384
  - Thomas Burt to Arthur G. Symonds; signed postcard, 1882 February 15; 11390 (Folder 1)
  - G.O. Trevelyan to Arthur G. Symonds; handwritten letter, signed, 1885 March 19; 11389 (Folder 1)
  - R. Reid to Arthur G. Symonds; handwritten letter, signed, 1885 May 13; 11388 (Folder 1)
  - Henry Richard to "Dear Sir"; handwritten letter, signed, 1887 June 28; 11387 (Folder 1)
  - Joseph E. Biggar to Arthur G. Symonds; handwritten letter, signed, 1889 May 14; 11386 (Folder 1)
  - William Gladstone to Arthur G. Symonds; handwritten note, signed, 1889 November 20; 11385 (Folder 1)
- Series II: Letters, 1901-1913, 11358
  - George Lewis to Arthur G. Symonds; handwritten letter, signed, 1901 September 15; 11383 (Folder 1)
  - Goldwin Smith to Arthur G. Symonds; handwritten letter, signed, 1901 October 9; 11382 (Folder 1)
  - John Clifford to Arthur G. Symonds; handwritten letter, signed, 1902 November 17; 11381 (Folder 1)
  - Montague Butler to Noel Buxton; handwritten letter, signed, 1903 September 18; 11380 (Folder 1)
  - Drummond Wolff to Noel Buxton; handwritten letter signed, 1903 September 24; 11379 (Folder 1)
  - J. Hereford to Noel Buxton; handwritten letter, signed, 1903 September 24; 11378 (Folder 1)
  - Carid to "Dear Sir"; handwritten letter, signed, 1903 September 25; 11377 (Folder 1)
  - Randall Cantaur to Bishop of Worcester; handwritten letter, signed, 1903 September 25; 11376 (Folder 1)
  - H. Hensley Henson to "Dear Sir"; handwritten letter, signed, 1903 September 26; 11375 (Folder 1)
  - E. Grey to "My dear Bryce"; handwritten letter, signed, 1903 September 27; 11374 (Folder 1)
  - A. Exon to "My dear Bryce"; handwritten letter, signed, 1903 September 28; 11373 (Folder 1)
  - Randall Cantaur to "Dear Sir", handwritten letter, signed, 1903 September 30; 11372 (Folder 1)
  - Hugh Cecil to Noel Buxton; handwritten letter, signed, 1904 March 18; 11371 (Folder 1)
  - John Clifford to Arthur G. Symonds; typed letter, signed, 1904 June 11; 11370 (Folder 1)
  - Surendranath Banerjea to Arthur G. Symonds; handwritten letter; signed, 1907 June 30; 11369 (Folder 1)
  - A.F. Tardon to Noel Buxton; handwritten letter; signed, 1907 September 20; 11368 (Folder 1)
  - R.B. Haldane to Scott James; handwritten letter, signed, 1907 September 26; 11367 (Folder 1)
  - Surendranath Banerjea to Arthur G. Symonds; typed letter, signed, 1909 July 2; 11366 (Folder 1)
  - Surendranath Banerjea to Arthur G. Symonds, handwritten, signed, 1909 July 19; 11365 (Folder 1)
  - M. Ealcat to "Dear Sir"; handwritten letter, signed, 1911 November 14; 11364 (Folder 1)
  - Djouid Sey to Noel Buxton; typed letter, signed, 1911 December 11; 11363 (Folder 1)
  - M. Javid to "Dear Sir"; handwritten letter, signed, 1911 December 14; 11362 (Folder 1)
  - Randall Cantaur to Noel Buxton; handwritten letter, signed, 1913 January 20; 11361 (Folder 1)
  - Hugh Cecil to "Dear Sir"; handwritten letter, signed, Circa 1904; 11360 (Folder 1)
  - J. Bryce to Arthur G. Symonds; handwritten letter, signed, [no year] August 17; 11359 (Folder 1)